[country music]
[Peter] So Eric,
this is all your family's property?
-Yep. I'm a sixth generation Waterman,
and we've owned the same piece of property
since Winslow Waterman came over
from North Haven and bought it
from one of Henry Knox's war buddies.
-You guys even have
an island out here, right?
It's this one right here
with the trees, Eben Island.
-We're going to get out there?
-Yep. Better start swimming.
-[Peter laughs]
That's Tommy Island.
Just one house on it?
Yeah. Trip family built a house out there,
and I got a camp over on there.
-So deep history here.
A lot of entrenched families.
Been here generations.
It's changing. Used to be more,
but I think we're the last holdout.
-You're the last holdout?
-Yep.
I have three sisters,
and we all own this together.
These old barns, everyone says,
"Oh, it's too bad to let them go."
But, man,
we're gonna have to tear them down.
-How many acres do you guys have?
-We only have three and a half acres
of original farmland here.
-New houses like that? What's that story?
My grandparents passed away,
and the family had an opportunity
to buy the house, but nobody bought it.
Someone from out of state
came and bought it.
Probably $4 million.
-$4 million?!
-I'm not kidding. It's unreal.
-So this is totally in transition.
You got the old trailer here.
You've got the new $4 million place.
We call this the Waterman Beach Ghetto.
We already went through it.
It's not very big.
-If you blink, you'll miss it.
-All right.
So is that the story right now
up here in Maine?
You've got the old local families,
and then second home type stuff?
Yeah. We're dwindling.
It's just like my daughter.
She's going to school in Rhode Island.
She's probably not gonna live here.
My daughter Abby, I'm pretty sure will.
'cause she fishes and has her own boat.
-How old is your daughter?
-21. You'll see her boat.
-She's going to go with us.
-We're going to see her today?
Yeah.
This was all family, distant cousins.
I had to go three counties over
to find a girl
I wasn't related to for a girlfriend.
-Really?
[laughing] No. Third cousins don't count.
This is the Gig Village.
It's the Wessaweskeag River. Indian name.
And there's George Kittredge's
yellow submarine.
What's going on with this?
That was a great friend of my father's.
He was in World War II.
He was a commander of two submarines.
He had a submarine school.
He visioned people being able to
explore underwater by themselves.
-That is cool. Look at that.
-He had a subtender.
He'd put them on the stern of the boat.
-All right.
That's his railway.
That's where he used to haul his…
-Sweet.
-We went out and salvaged
a sunk boat in 120 feet of water
when I was 13 years old.
-You want to go into Keeg's store?
-Not really.
What's in there?
Just a bunch of f*cking greasy locals.
-All out-of-staters.
-[Peter laughs]
We got better things to do.
-Okay. So right now,
what's the dynamic like?
Locals versus out-of-staters
or second homes or…
My dynamic is they say
good fences make good neighbors,
but I just think good neighbors
make good neighbors.
-Okay.
-Don't be a douche.
Right.
Treat people how you're treated.
And if they treat you like crap…
Double it up. Send it back.
But if they come in cool,
you guys are cool.
Oh, yeah. No, yeah.
There's no animosity, no anger.
That's what family's for.
[laughter]
So this is your place?
-Yeah, this is my house.
Yeah, my nice messy pad.
-Ah, that's cool. It's a nice place.
[plays piano]
I can't read music. I just mess around.
[continues playing]
That's about it.
There's a picture of… that crashed,
I don't know, 20, 30 miles offshore.
-Okay.
-My father got the last known location
from the Coast Guard,
and he went out in his lobster boat,
and right before dark, he found it.
He brought a pilot friend of his
who was a Navy pilot with him
in case they could
get it going and fly home.
-Nice.
Ended up towing it
into Criehavenen Harbor.
Put it on a moor and then sold it
back to the insurance company.
Everybody wins, right?
-What's the story with this wheel?
Ah, it's just decoration.
It's kind of a fishing house, isn't it?
-Yeah, but it's a nice one.
I've been in some fishing houses
where I got a buddy
in Smith Island, Maryland.
The water comes in his house and
the minnows come in with the big tides.
-Really?
-Yeah.
So your place is doing pretty well,
I gotta say.
Yeah. There's a Halibut on the wall.
A friend of mine's father made that.
That was me in high school,
hardhat diving.
When I was like 14.
And this is my boat.
Bought that boat when I was 19.
So this is funny. I found this picture.
That's me in the rigging
taking a picture with a throwaway camera.
And that's the picture I took.
-Oh, nice.
We were steaming into the sun.
It was Asher Alley.
He had a steel scallop dragger.
We're going to swing down.
Me and Peter are going to stop down
and you and I
are gonna swap a few stories.
-Oh, I thought you said
something about storage.
No, no.
There's none left upstairs. It's full.
-Okay.
-Oh, I'm right here.
-We'll talk to you later. In a minute.
-Yeah. Yeah, buddy.
-Who's this guy?
-Buzzy.
-Buzzy?
-Buzzy Kinney, yeah.
-Buzzy an old school local?
-Oh, yeah.
-You could make a whole show about him.
-About Buzzy?
He got his girlfriend pregnant.
He had to quit school to go to work.
I fished with him
since I was 10 years old.
[Peter] So you can make a good life
doing that here?
You can't come from away and do it
because rules and regulations
are so strict.
And being able to get licenses to do it.
And then you've got to be accepted.
You can't just go and say,
"Hey, I'm going to go lobstering."
It's very territorial.
Okay, so there's like some sort of
committee that figures that out?
No, it's just you fish where you're from.
Unless you buy into it.
It's a gentleman's agreement, basically.
Invisible lines.
-We use landmarks.
-Okay.
So you line up granny's house
on the point.
You know, use like landmarks,
like range marks, but…
-You guys respect that?
-Yeah, pretty good.
No one crosses the line?
All friendships end at the line.
If you don't know where the line is,
keep coming, you'll find it.
[Peter laughs]
Pull up alongside them with a
big old Dexter-Russell knife
on a stone, sharpening it up.
-You know?
-[sharpening sound]
-Okay.
-No, I don't.
That's what the old timers did.
-They fought over it?
-Yeah, it's not worth it. I don't fight.
-But look at this.
How it comes right into the bay.
It's very unique.
It's very specific to Maine, right?
All these rocky outcoves and whatnot.
-Mm-hmm. I think it's 3,500 miles
of coastline, I think.
-Yeah, and I forget it, but I think
it's something like 4,000 islands.
Like that many.
The winds Norwest.
-Are we looking okay?
-Oh, yeah, we'll be fine.
We're looking good?
-This cemetery, the land
was given to the town by my family.
-A lot of your family members here?
-Yeah. A lot of old names here.
The Overtons, they came from Finland.
-Oh, no way.
-Yeah.
-The Finns came here.
There was a lot of Finns,
Swedes, Norwegian.
The big thing was
working in the quarries, cutting granite.
-Oh, right.
I am a Waterman, Eric Waterman.
-Oh, no way.
That's your last name, that's right.
That's my father here.
My grandmother is beside him.
-Could you imagine living anywhere else?
No, not really. I don't know what I'd do.
-You're so rooted into this place, huh?
-Yeah.
I'm the last waterman.
There's no more. I have two daughters.
That's it. Last man standing.
This house on the right
is where Buzzy grew up.
Who we're going to see now.
His real name's Arnold.
They all called him Buzzy 'cause
his younger brother couldn't say brother.
He'd say buzza.
So they started calling him Buzzy.
I guess. I might be wrong.
So this is Sprucehead Bridge over there.
-Oh, okay.
This is beautiful.
-This is Buzzy's house on the right.
High school dropout.
-That is beautiful.
Look at his garden. He's doing all that?
-Yeah. His wife passed away,
and he's just kept her gardens going
to keep her memory alive,
'cause she loved her gardens.
Look at all these stones here.
This is beautiful, guys.
A true privilege to get in
with some of these old timers.
You don't just show up and get this,
so we're very lucky to have Eric today.
[Eric] How you doing, old boy?
No, I don't have anything to drink
other than water.
I got water in the truck.
I'll be all right.
[Peter] You want me to call you Buzzy?
[Buzzy] Hey, you.
-You want me to call you hey, you.
All right.
-Anything you want,
as long as I know you're talking to me.
-All right.
That's Buzzy back in the day.
Yeah. It looks like
I'm strangling him, but I'm not.
[Eric] No, he's not.
[Peter] How was it
back in the day lobstering?
A lot better than it is now.
[Eric] Yeah, for sure.
I struggle with change.
I like things the way they were
in the old days.
It's just like now when we ride to town,
you don't know anybody.
Ten years ago, fifteen years ago,
you'd be four or five cars
that you would pass in either way
that you knew the people.
Now they're all strangers.
You go into Walmart
and you don't hardly know anybody.
In the old days, you just knew everybody.
-Even out here?
Oh yes.
-Guys like Eric
still sticking around though.
I'm not going to do anything else.
That's his lifestyle.
That's what he wants to do and this is
what we was all born and brought up with.
I haven't been able to go now
for seven years.
My wife got colon cancer
and so I had to give up.
She dealt with cancer for
what, eight years?
-Seven or eight years.
-Gotcha.
Rather than have
somebody else take care of her.
we kept her right to home.
We don't realize how nice we have it.
We always want more.
But the little things in life since
I lost her a little over six years ago,
the little things we take for granted.
-Like what?
Hmph.
Coming home from a day's work
and having your supper already
setting at the table and eating
with your wife and going to bed
and doing things in the yard
and it's just totally, totally,
different.
And she got what she wanted
and she built all of these gardens
and did she do it to get even
with me for some reason?
'Cause now I'm trying to take care of it
and I don't know one from another.
I really don't. Well that's… [scoffs]
-Dandelions and…
-Oh yeah.
I know tulips.
And she told me what to do and I did it.
And that's what I tell everybody now.
I was a moldable male.
There's three ways to do something.
The right way, the wrong way,
Buzzy's way. The hard way.
[laughing] The hard way, yeah.
-You miss being out at sea all the time?
I'm getting older.
In a certain sense, yes.
Because that's all you dealt with
was what was right there.
-Yeah.
Would you guys suggest
someone get into this industry now or now?
-No.
Abby, she's fishing but
I don't think it will ever be
her main source of income.
She's going to school
and fishing on her own in the summer.
But throw everything on the line.
[Buzzy] You have to make the decision.
My wife told me what to do and I did it.
You put me in my boat and send me
out to haul and I had no trouble.
Mother Nature told me what to do.
-You like the simplicity of it?
Yes. Yeah.
-Life was pretty straight forward.
-Yes.
And you know your family needed money.
We needed groceries.
And we didn't get any food stamps
or any federal assistance.
We earned everything
'cause that's the way it was.
Now, you go to the federal government
and they'll give you a coupon.
You can go into Walmart
and load your grocery cart up
with anything you want
and they pay for it.
When we was kids and when we was
first married and growing up,
you needed food, you went and earned it.
-So you're seeing a lot of that in Maine?
I see it in my own neighborhood.
But when I'm in the grocery store
and see all these people with their carts
and they're buying drinking water.
And I don't.
I drink what comes out of the faucet.
-[Eric] Hard to tell.
-[Buzzy laughs] Yeah.
All right, Buzzy.
Nice. That's a firm grip.
You want arm wrestle?
Here you go, Eric.
Now I'm 85 years old.
-You count.
-One, two, three.
Okay.
-Go.
-Come on now.
[laughs] Nice.
Buzzy locked in.
I don't want to go too hard, Buzzy.
But that is…
You got a lot of strength still.
Take care. Don't crush my hand.
Why?
Well, you can if you want.
[Eric] Toxic masculinity.
80 odd years old.
Yeah, something's happened.
Yeah.
Yeah. I'm out on the back porch
with Eric Waterman
and some guy from Nebraska.
[Peter laughs]
Okay. Okay.
Hey, Buzz.
Always remember. Never forget.
There's a sucker born every minute
and two ready to take him on.
I taught you well.
-[Abby] Hi.
-[Peter] How you doing?
-Good. How are you?
-Good.
-Abby.
-Peter. Nice to meet you.
I'm having a good time
with your dad today.
-Picked a good day, didn't he?
-Yeah. Really nice out. [giggles]
-Abby, how long you been doing this for?
Since I was like 10.
-No way.
-Yeah.
-Do you love it?
-I love it.
You can't really not.
-You can't not? What do you love about it?
That it's outside.
That I get to do it with family
and close family friends.
I don't know where this hook is.
Just drag it with my hands.
[Peter] How's it been out here?
Good summer?
[man] We're in pogie season now.
The boats bring in,
get fish in their nets.
-Okay.
So these guys just caught these?
-Yeah. These guys hauled
a couple hundred traps.
-Nice.
What's the value of lobster right now?
-Well, that's all a matter of perspective.
If you're a fisherman,
the price is $5.75 on the slip,
and they usually get
a little bit extra for good lobsters.
So roughly $6 a pound in each crate.
We weigh them out to 90 pound crates.
-Okay, and then in a restaurant, how much?
In a restaurant, a two lobster dinner
could cost you 50 bucks.
-Who's making all the money
in this industry?
Every set of hands makes a little.
-Peter?
-Yeah.
-I watch your stuff.
Oh, thank you, brother. What's your name?
-My name's Carey.
-Carey.
-Can I take a look at those guys?
-Sure.
-Oh, nice.
-They send them up to us as close to
90 pounds as they can get them eyeballing.
And then we take them
to the scales and weigh them.
-Okay, and then where do they go?
We take them off the scales,
take them to our tank house out back,
which is basically
a lobster swimming pool.
Then we put it on a truck
to ship it out from here.
Where do they end up eventually?
-Oh, they've been all over the world.
-All over the world?
So why are they moving so fast right now?
It's just how it is.
For them,
more than anybody, time is money.
If they screw around
and let the lobsters drain out,
they're going to lose their water weight.
Makes out better for the company,
but worse for them.
-Understood.
Abby's a lobster fisherman.
She owns a boat.
I know.
We're getting out with her right now.
-Wow.
Abby, what do you think
of their technique?
I think that they're both very smart men.
That's another father and son duo.
[man] I'm blushing. I'm embarrassed.
I'm going to go home and grieve.
-That's father and son duo?
-Yeah.
And then Junior's taking over.
Yep. No, he already did.
-I have no power.
-[Abby giggles]
[Peter] Lookit, there we go.
Right out to the Atlantic.
So many islands out there.
So much beauty here in Maine.
And it's great to see that so many people
are still doing this for work.
And it seems like a thriving industry.
I believe it goes up the shore
for quite a ways
where there are fishermen and lobstermen.
And it really is a culture.
It's really like its own unique thing.
And very much a multi-generational task.
So, they're setting up the boat.
We're almost ready to go.
Going out to the lobster traps.
Going out to their island
with their home on it,
which I'm really excited to see.
And Eric wanted me to tell you,
"Hey, let everyone know
that we don't go out fishing this late.
It's only 'cause, you came up
from Portland this morning.
Usually we're at the crack of dawn."
So, there you go.
And also, something I want to tell you
while we're waiting.
I might be seeing you this week.
Book tour is happening. If you're
watching this, Day of posting, Saturday.
Next week, I'm hitting the road
New York, Boston,
Greater Chicago, Greater Detroit,
Greater Phoenix.
Hopefully more locations coming soon.
For book signing,
Your Fellow Americans tour.
A chance for us to meet in person.
Scan the code here
on your television or whatever device
you're watching on or link down below.
That ticket gets you a book,
a signed copy from me.
Us meeting each other in person.
A handshake, high five, your choice.
And just a great experience
to finally connect in the flesh and blood.
And it's happening so soon.
And the weather turned
a bit for the worse,
but doesn't look like rain.
I think we'll be good.
Abby, what are you doing there?
I'm filling the bait bags with pogies.
So this is what we'll put on the trap
to bait the lobsters.
And putting them in bait bags
makes it last longer.
So they don't all get eaten
within like a day or two.
-Okay, so it's harder
to get through the bag?
-Yeah.
-Gotcha.
[Eric] See this house
with the little front porch?
-Yeah.
-That was my great grandfather's.
-No way.
-And that to the left is his workshop.
-That's his workshop? That was his house?
And I asked like 15, maybe 20 years ago,
the guy who owns this mooring right here,
where my skiff is.
-That's your skiff?
-If he ever sold it, I wanted to buy it.
Because that was where
my great grandfather kept his boat.
-Wow.
That's Abby's boat right there.
-Abby, that's your boat?
Yep, First Shot.
-First Shot. So you go out solo mission?
I take somebody with me,
but yes, I run the boat.
When did you get your first lobster boat?
Probably when I was like 12 or 13.
My dad got me an outboard
with a little hauler on it.
Like 15 feet long.
And then that's my next one.
I got that one in 2022.
-So it's more important
to have a boat than a car, right?
Yeah. Nicer boat than nicer car.
[Eric] This is my scallop dragger here.
So different boats take on
a different functionality for fishing.
-Yeah.
Different strokes for different folks.
-There you go.
If I was scallop diving,
I'd go jump off this hard spot right here.
So it's just gotten better
with the technology?
Yeah. It's made it a lot easier
for dumb people to do good.
This is a progression of electronics.
This was popular
in the, I'd say like the 90s.
And then this is like the next step up.
-Why do you keep this old stuff?
Out of respect for the guy that owned
the boat. It's just like part of the boat.
And I'm just so stubborn. I just held off.
I was like, I don't need that.
I don't need that.
-I've been doing it this way.
-Right.
Kind of like Buzzy.
[country music]
[Eric] Hang on.
[music continues]
[Eric] Wow. Nothing.
[Eric] Wow. Worse than I thought.
[pully wheel whirs]
[Peter] But they ate all the food, right?
[Abby] Most of it.
[Eric] Short.
They're all short.
-Okay, so if they're not long enough,
you gotta throw them back?
Yeah. I can tell by looking
that this is probably the only one.
Short, short, short.
It's a hard time where we are.
We're just kind of baiting and waiting.
And these haven't set very long either.
I hauled them five nights ago.
There's more there.
Nope.
Bless it.
That's a female.
See the eggs under the tail?
-Oh yeah. So you can't take the females?
So that's what we do.
See this flipper right here?
-See how there's no notch in it?
-Yep.
I'm gonna put a notch in that and that way
after she drops her eggs,
nobody can keep it.
-That means it had eggs on it.
-Okay.
So it protects our industry.
These are breeders.
This is a small lobster for having eggs.
-Right.
Look at all those eggs. It's beautiful.
I'll show you. I'll just go like this.
[Peter] Okay so this shows
everyone else out here…
-So even after she drops her eggs
you can't keep it.
Okay. If I didn't do that,
she dropped her eggs.
So you flip it over,
there's no eggs but it has a notch,
you gotta throw it back.
-Everyone plays by those rules?
Not… I mean…
Nobody has to notch them but
people, a lot of people do.
You'll catch a lot of notched lobsters.
That one's just a little bit under.
I don't know. [sighs]
You get claws,
it's like one claw that's we call it junk.
-Right.
-It's not nice.
You'll get a run of nice clean lobsters.
You got these ones with barnacles.
They've been just laying around here.
They're not moving much.
Yep.
That's my end marker, that means
that's the last buoy in the string.
Everyone's gotta put their name
and number on those buoys.
-So you can come out, you can go
all the way out here and get nothing.
That happens?
Not usually, but sometimes.
You'll get something.
-So there are days you're losing money.
Yeah, yeah. Like today.
It's my day off.
I'm not supposed to make any money.
Come on, baby.
Oh, there's gotta be one in there.
I see one. I see one right there.
There's one right there.
See, there's a male.
I can tell by looking at it.
It indicates it's a male.
-You sell this to the fish market, right?
-Yeah.
-Okay, how much
would that one go for, roughly?
-Seven bucks probably.
The price is $5.75 a pound
-Okay.
And then at a restaurant,
that's like 30 bucks, 40 bucks?
Yeah. When you eliminate
the middleman, you win.
But we don't have time and
we're not set up to 'cause you could
sell them straight to the restaurants,
we'd make a lot more money, but
then you gotta have
your own docks to go out of.
It's a lot of time.
I mean, I sell them
here and there to people.
There's a campground down the road.
Put the cooler in the back of my Pontiac
and go for a little cruise
and sell them lobsters fresh off the boat.
-Have a drink with them.
-Oh, nice.
It makes it more enjoyable.
A little side hustle. You know.
[Eric] Where we headed, Peter?
I don't know.
[in Maine accent]
You can't get there from here.
[Eric laughs]
-Good shot.
-Was that good?
-Yeah, good enough.
Okay, check this out.
We're going here at Eben Island
and Eric's last name, Waterman.
That's how tied in to this place he is.
So, Eric, this is your family island?
-Yeah, my sisters and I own it.
Is that common in Maine?
You own your own island?
-No, not really.
Not for a local to own an island.
Out-of-staters, yeah, it's quite common.
Alright.
How many guys are out here like you?
You got your name on the map, basically.
Six generations.
There's not as many as there was.
You know, like, in Buzzy's time,
there was a lot of generational families
fishing and working together.
There's still a fair amount.
Most of the harbor, I would say,
is at least second-generation fishermen.
We're gonna have to paddle this thing
like a canoe getting out of here.
Land ho!
Go ahead, Abby, bail.
Look at that.
There's a wish rock for you.
-Oh, nice.
-It's got a white band all the way around.
-Make a wish.
-Good luck?
How often do you guys come out here?
He stays out here sometimes.
-No way.
-I just come.
When I get in from haul,
I'll go into the dock, sell my lobsters,
drop my stern man off,
go to my house, take a shower,
grab some groceries or whatever
and come back out.
-And you just totally cut free out here?
-Yeah, you can walk around naked
if you want, not us, but…
You're the only one out here.
Permission only.
-Okay, so this has
been in the family forever.
My mother had some money
squirreled away for our college.
I think she bought it in 1979.
Fairly cheap.
This little workshop here I built
a couple years ago with a friend of mine.
-That's the shop?
-Yeah, just a little generator.
-This is a man cave.
-A man cave on your own island is sweet.
-Yeah.
A hot summer day,
sit here in the shade with the door open
and just stare at the water.
Are you sick of lobster at this point
or do you love eating them?
I usually eat them about twice a year
but I eat as many as I possibly can.
-Just twice a year?
Yeah. I like ribeyes. [chuckles]
Who doesn't, right?
-And you built this?
-Yeah.
Nice.
Friends helped with the shingling.
Oh, the shag's down there.
-That island over there, same situation?
-That's Tommy. These islands both
used to be owned by Ebenezer Thorndike
and he had a son named Eben
and a son named Thomas
and he named the islands after his sons.
-Okay.
And he also owned Matinic Island
and Ebenezer,
he got here because of Henry Knox.
He was the Secretary of War
for George Washington.
He settled up here,
they built a great big mansion
on the river in Thomaston,
St. George River.
That's where the original was
and they built a replica
in Thomaston on the hill.
And it's a museum.
And so they wanted
to get this place settled.
Get some people up here
and Eben was buddies with Henry Knox
and he said come on up,
stake out a chunk of land
and that's what he did.
You got islands,
you got all kinds of land and
there's a cemetery off Waterman's
Beach Road named Thorndike Cemetery.
-Okay.
-Like hidden, you know.
I think it might be
the oldest one in town.
This is like my carpentry skills.
Can you see?
-Oh, this is great.
Just rustic and simple.
-When I get a good glow going
I fire that speaker up
and put it on the porch and people text me
song requests it's so loud.
I get texts from that island,
I get texts from Sprucehead Island,
from the campground.
-What are you playing?
-Rock and roll, whatever they want.
Island DJ.
It's great.
This is in case anybody ever gets
blown ashore and gets stranded.
-Right.
At least they'll have a good time.
[laughs]
-What's up here?
-Check it out.
It's just a little loft with some beds.
[Peter] This is great.
You got a couple more beds.
Kite on a fishing pole. That's genius.
-You got your own beach?
-Yeah.
We'll have lobster out here though.
We'll cook them on the beach,
clams and lobsters.
-Water's cold.
-[Abby] Oh, yeah.
That's like low 50s.
Yeah, it's low 50s right now.
You can catch lobsters like right here.
-Just right here?
-Yeah.
So if I moved up here to Maine
and I'm like I want to start
lobster fishing is it impossible?
It would be for you because
you'd be holding the camera in one hand
and you'd need both hands to fish.
If I drop the camera
I'm like I'm done with that.
And I just wanted to fish.
Is there a way in?
Well there is but it's federal.
You'd have to fish federal waters
and then you can't bring…
But in your zone here
I wouldn't be able to do anything.
No, that's it.
-That's good for you guys.
-It seems like they put a limit
on licenses and more people showed up.
-Okay.
That's how we lock things in Maine.
Those are to just keep honest people out.
You got pretty much no crime
up in these parts?
Yeah we do. It's getting worse but
it's more in Rockland and more and more
drug boss people
in their cars bringing drugs in.
It's like a random road stop
and they're finding
large amounts of drugs.
-But up in this town?
-It's pretty good around here.
They stick out like a sore thumb.
Right.
[Eric] Guess we'll paddle on back out.
This used to be a German lady,
Joe and Hilda.
I used to work for her after he died
when I was a kid.
Clearing her land and stuff.
There used to be a sheep farm.
They had an immaculate sheep farm.
And then she sold the farm
and they rebuilt.
They built this thing.
I think he's
the highest taxpayer in the town.
And then if you look to the left,
there's another house up in there.
I think there's three places
on the property.
You find arrowheads,
Indian artifacts along the shore there.
Found them on Eben Island.
Found them up the river.
-You found them on your island?
Arrowheads? Wow.
-I found a perfect one out there.
-Who was here?
-Was it Abenaki?
-Yeah.
Penawapskewi Indians, they found…
Spalding Island's right over there.
-There's a shell pile. You know?
-Yeah.
The guy was out there,
I don't know 30 years ago.
He saw a bone
sticking out of the shell pile.
And he told someone that was into
artifact hunting that knew a lot about it.
He went out there and excavated it.
It was a skeleton.
And I think
one of the universities out West,
they were able to do a DNA test
on it inside one of the bones
or marrow or whatever was left, something.
And it came back as part
Native American and part Viking.
-Oh, interesting.
And this is where we started.
Right up here somewhere?
-Yeah. Right here.
-That's all your family property
back there?
-This house out front isn't.
The house in behind is my sister's.
The house was partially built
with parts from shipwrecks.
-Oh, no way.
-Our name went on the chart
because of that name, Thorndike.
Thorndike Point,
Waterman Point, Waterman's Beach.
They got the land from Thorndike
when this town first started.
-You sort of have some rank here,
don't you?
No, but it doesn't matter to anybody.
Nobody cares about
your family history or your heritage
or how long you've been somewhere.
Everybody's after the almighty dollar.
And it shows. You can see it in people.
They don't give a sh*t.
Growing up around this place
and knowing my uncles and my aunts
and my grandparents,
if I could go back,
I would have spent a lot more time
talking to them and learning.
Closer you get to the source,
the more accurate the reporting is.
So, by the time it trickles down,
you can even relate it to the Bible.
I mean, look how many times
that story's changed. So…
I hope my kids continue that trend.
[Peter] How's fishing right now?
What's going on out there, buddy?
Well, not much really.
-Really?
-At least we're getting 'em.
-Is this your sister?
-Yep, that's Nora.
-You guys fish together?
-Yep.
Who's better or not better
or worse? It's like you work together.
-We're even.
-Yes.
You're out there tomorrow?
We're going out Monday.
You're getting the boat ready for Monday?
Yep. Boats.
We have the Descendant
and we have the old spec.
Then you got the Nora June,
my grandfather.
Then you got the Horizon,
my uncle right there.
-You're the next generation
fishing out here.
-I think we're like the tenth generation.
-You think you're tenth?!
We believe so.
We aren't actually sure,
but we've been fishing
for many, many years.
-What's your last name?
-McLennan.
M-C-L-E-N-N-A-N.
-Okay.
What do you think about this year, Nora?
Been a good year.
Haven't catched much lobsters, but…
-We got one today.
Wow.
What do you think of that?
Eh… [chuckles]
Have you ever seen it that bad?
Yeah, actually we got four pounds
out of ten traps one day.
Well, we didn't even get a pound.
Yeah, that's…
Yeah, you did worse than us.
That's for sure.
So we fished worse than
you've ever fished in your life.
-Yeah, just about.
-Probably.
-Pretty much.
-In that one haul.
-Well, truth hurts.
-But keep it up out there.
-Thank you.
Without you guys fishing
we're not gonna eat good seafood.
Right.
-You're the mother? Thank you for that.
-Yeah.
That was really cool. They're awesome.
-Bye.
-See you, guys.
[Eric] And this, my friend,
is what this town is turning into.
That.
-Right.
-Not the prettiest.
[Eric] Really expensive,
on one acre of land.
-You're saying four mil?
-Yeah, it's unreal.
-And now we're going full circle, Eric.
-To peace, harmony,
and happiness right here.
-And you stay here too?
Yeah, I got a bed in there.
-Get out!
-I'll let you check it out.
Maine humor.
[Peter laughs]
Okay, Mass… Mass hole.
Masshole, yeah.
See? Maintain.
-Maintain and Mass hole.
-Yeah.
Don't you have a bunch of Mass friends,
you were saying?
Yeah, I gave a couple to my buddies,
they're on Wicked Tuna.
They thought they were funnier than hell.
-Okay, so Eric…
-They have a certain type of personality.
I don't give those
to everybody from Mass.
[Peter laughs]
Okay,
so you're saying here's the friction,
big money coming in from other places.
Yeah, well this is a perfect example.
I get along with those people great.
I don't… But this isn't…
I've been here my whole life so far.
This is just what's happening to me.
It's like Vermont and it's probably
happening in New Hampshire.
They buy a second home
and they turn it into the Taj Mahal, so…
It doesn't bother me.
I get more joy out of this
than they do out of that.
-This is your Taj?
-This is my Taj Mahal.
-Let's check it out.
Oh, look at that. That's the view.
What would it take?
Everyone's got a price
with their real estate.
If your neighbors gave you six mil,
you're gonna leave, aren't you?
-No.
-Come on.
Six mil is not much money.
I could blow through that
in two years in Vegas. No.
-What would be the price
to sell this shack?
Lifetime supply of White Claw. No.
[laughter]
I don't have one.
-You wouldn't no matter what?
You're going to stand firm on principles?
And hold out. You thinking about
buying some land in Maine?
I'm not. I just test people
on this question all the time.
-I'm too stubborn.
-I was just in the Arkansas Delta.
And they're putting solar panels
up over the farmer's fields
and the farmer wasn't happy about it.
And I'm like, there's a price
that you'd sell, wouldn't you?
And he's like, nah, nah.
And then I pushed on.
He's like, yeah, five mil,
you know…
But you're saying no, Eric.
If they were willing to pay
five million or six million for this,
I'd sell them some land somewhere else.
Not this.
There's not many
generational Mainers that can
look at the ocean
from their camp or house.
I could build a house here if I want.
I have a house right up the road.
I'm less than a mile from my house
and it's like being in a whole nother…
You know, a whole nother place.
I could walk to my house.
I could ride a four-Wheeler
through the woods to my house.
So…
-So people might think it was all…
might sound like a douche right now
but people might say
that it was all given to you, right?
You didn't have to work for it.
Yeah, I haven't worked for anything.
It's all just fallen in my lap.
I never met a banker I liked.
But I've met a lot of them. [laughs]
No, I've had some help.
But I had to prove myself.
I'm very fortunate.
I'm lucky. I'm blessed.
And… I'm proud.
You just gotta put your head down
and keep on going.
You got your ups and downs.
It's just like the stock market.
But you find the level
and just hold there and maintain.
Today's catch, we'll call it a down
but it was a good experience.
Yeah, we just went for the experience.
If you really want to see some action
you gotta come up in probably like
three and a half weeks from now.
-Okay. Can we go in?
-Yeah.
Another Maine lock, see?
No one can get in.
-It's locked.
-[Peter chuckles]
And this is the… You sleep down here?
-Yes!
-This is great!
It's just everything you need.
Simple as it comes.
It's awesome. I got a guitar there.
I could embarrass myself playing that.
-There's a couple photos I took.
-"You suck less than most people."
Yeah, that's good friends
giving me that for my birthday.
I thought it was great
so I put it up there.
That's Joe DiMaggio's nephew.
A good friend of mine. He passed away.
His father was Dom DiMaggio.
He played for the Yankees.
He had a house on Sprucehead Island
and he built a log cabin
on Waterman's Beach Road down here.
And that's the Constitution.
I built that in high school.
It's just everything's miniature.
Look at this thing.
A little bigger than my hand,
but it's perfect.
It's all you need.
It's old school tiny house.
-This is so cool.
This is an old school tiny house, right?
Alright, Eric.
Anything else you want to say?
Always be good to people
because you don't know what
anyone's been through except yourself.
-That's true.
If anyone wants to get one
of your fine hats here…
Are you selling
the limited edition Massachusetts hat?
Might be too offensive to some.
I know how sensitive people are
and there's a lot of Karens and
thin-skinned people in the world.
For those that are,
they can buy the hat from you. Okay.
Ask for the vulgar edition of…
Okay. Or if they want to go
a little lighter on the…
-All different colors.
-Okay. Cool.
Pick the colors.
Mix and match. Maintain.
And then, all of you,
hope to see you next week.
Which is crazy.
I'm doing a book tour, Eric.
-Yeah?
-Yeah. I'm going all over the country.
For the first time,
I'm not gonna be behind the screen.
-I'm actually meeting people in person.
-Yeah.
You should practice shaking hands
like with Buzzy. I bet you…
Buzzy had a strong shake.
Nice shake, Eric.
-Thanks for today. Appreciate it, bro.
-You're welcome.
And this is part of
a greater Maine series.
Portland, Lewiston,
a mill town
that I'm going to in a couple days,
and then far north.
So, five different Maines,
five different stories.
-Thanks, Eric.
-You're welcome. Come again.
Thanks for coming along, guys.
Until the next one.
[country music]